Guide to the Walter Francis Willcox papers, 1886-1960.
Willcox, Walter Francis papers, 1886-1960.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Walter Francis Willcox papers, 1886-1960.
14-10-504 & 14-10-821
Walter Francis Willcox, 1861-1964.
7 cubic ft.; 16 reels negative microfilm; 4 tape recordings; 4 folders.
Correspondence, tributes, articles, notes, genealogies.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Papers concerning Willcox's career as professor of economics and statistics at Cornell, including extensive material on American social and political issues, as well as Willcox's personal and family papers.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of economics and statistics at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, tributes, printed and draft articles and notes, and genealogies and other family papers. Subjects include Willcox's involvement in the United States census of 1900, the International Statistical Institute, Amherst College alumni activity, and statistical analysis of various social problems, including the registration of births and deaths and voter registration, Afro-American crime statistics, race relations, and Prohibition.
The collection also includes tape recordings celebrating Willcox's 90th, 95th, and 100th birthdays; family correspondence, including letters to and from Alice Eloise Work (Mrs. Walter Willcox), and his son Bertram F. who was in France with the American Ambulance Field Service.
Also, material relating to his work with the William Allen White Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies, comment on American political practices and statecraft, addresses and articles pertaining to Cornell University, and work concerning Congressional reapportionment. Tape recordings pertain to Andrew Dickson White, Jacob Gould Schurman, and Charles Kendall Adams.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Willcox, Walter Francis, 1861-1964.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Willcox family.; Willcox, Bertram F.; Work family.; Work, Alice Eloise.; American Ambulance Field Service.; Amherst College--Alumni.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Dept. of Economics.; International Statistical Institute.; William Allen White Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies.
Subjects:
Statistics.; Census--1900.; Afro-Americans.; Vital statistics.; Prohibition.; Criminal statistics--United States.; Political science--United States.; Afro-American criminals.; Family--New York (State).; Apportionment (Election law)--United States.; Voter registration--United States.; Race relations--United States.; Professors emeriti.; Economists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Tributes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collections #14-10-821, #14-10-mf32, #14-10-tr24, tr25, tr23, and tr22, and #14-10-m.76, m.376, and m.466.
CONTAINER LIST
- Collection Number: 14-10-504
  - St-W correspondence re statistics and reapportionment for U.S. Congress (Box 1)
  - Genealogical material re folder of Wilcox family letters, 1804-1848?; Statistical notes (Box 2)
  - A-Work Genealogical files (Box 3)
  - W correspondence (personal and family). Including Anne Goodenow letters (typescript, 2 folders) and 2 envelopes of letters to Mary A. Wilcox re genealogy (Box 4)
- Collection Number: 14-10-821
  - Correspondence and papers
    - Holmes Family. Letters (transcripts), 1818-1843 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Holmes Family. Genealogy and Biography Notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Holmes Family. Career of John Holmes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Holmes Family, correspondence relating to, 1925-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Holmes Family. Description of Holmes House, Alfred, Maine (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Willcox Family. Recollections of Willcox Home, Kennebunk, Maine, by Mary A. Willcox (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Willcox Family. Miscellaneous papers (includes "Willcox-Work Family Lines") (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - William Henry Willcox. Autobiography, (manuscript) 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - William Henry Willcox. Autobiography, (typescript) 1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - William Henry Willcox. Autobiography, (typescript) 1901 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - William Henry Willcox-Anne Goodenow Letters (transcripts), 1852-1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - William Henry Willcox-Anne Goodenow Letters (transcripts); 1857-1859, 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Letters from and about Wm. H. Willcox, Wm. G. Willcox;" 1855, 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Anne Holmes Goodenow Willcox. Autobiography (typescript), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Anne Holmes Goodenow Willcox. Autobiography (typescript), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Willcox Family Life by Mary A. Willcox (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Walter Francis Willcox. Letters; 1878-1880, 1884-1887, 1893, 1896-1898, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Walter Francis Willcox. Letters (transcripts). 1878-1880 (valedictory), 1880-1887, 1892, 1893, 1896-1898, 1901, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters and Papers, Jan. 1888-May 1889 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, July 1889-Aug. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Sept. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Oct. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Nov. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Dec. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Jan. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Feb. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Mar. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Apr. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, May 1890 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, June 1890 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, July 1890, Sept. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Oct. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Nov. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Dec. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, (typescript), Apr. 1891-July 1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, (typescript), July 1891-Oct. 1891 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Nov. 1891 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Dec. 1891 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Jan. 1892 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Feb. 1892 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, Mar. 1892 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Alice Eloise Work. Letters, July 1892, Dec. 1892, Aug. 1893 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters; 1896, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, May 1901 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, June 1901 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, Aug. 1901 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters, Sept. 1901 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Alice Work Willcox. Letters; 1902, 1905, 1906, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Bertram F. Willcox. Letters; 1917, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - William G. Willcox. Tributes, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence; 1925, 1931, 1933, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, Jan. 1935-June 1935 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, July 1935-Dec. 1935, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, Jan. 1940-June 1940 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, July 1940-Dec. 1940, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence; 1950, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence; 1953, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, Sir Alfred Zimmern, 1953-1957; (also Zimmern's writings) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence; 1959, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Sociedad Mexicana de Geografia y Estadistica," letter, diploma, identification card, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Tributes on 80th Birthday, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, 85th Birthday, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, 90th Birthday, Addresses, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Correspondence, re Address, "Comments on speech at ninetieth anniversary dinner, Mar. 22, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Walter Family Letters re Walter F. Willcox bibliography, Will, and 96th Birthday; 1955, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Walter F. Willcox re "95th Birthday Comments," 1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Walter F. Willcox, 95th Birthday: Addresses by Robert E. Cushman and Frederick G. Marcham (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Walter F. Willcox, 100th Birthday, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Walter F. Willcox, Transcript of tape recorded interview, Mar. 23, 1957 (with "William Allan and Mary Willcox interview") (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Walter F. Willcox. "Worksheets" (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Greeting Cards (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Walter F. Willcox's Autobiographical Material (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Walter F. Willcox's Autobiographical Material (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Walter F. Willcox's Autobiographical Material, "Early Life," etc. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Walter F. Willcox's Autobiographical Material, "Confessions of an Octogenarian," "The Stone Will Case," etc. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Walter F. Willcox's Autobiography - Drafts, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Reapportionment Letters to New York Times, May 22, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Walter F. Willcox. "A Notable College Class" (Amherst, 1884 ) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Walter F. Willcox. "The Teaching of Economics, Political and Social Science at Cornell University" (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Clippings (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Clippings: Robert Frost, Franklin D. Roosevelt (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Volume V Clippings" (Editorials), 1939-1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Included in Volume V" (Editorials), 1940 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Apportionment Statistics (negatives) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Walter F. Willcox. Photographs (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Willcox Family Photos (Box 6, Folder 15-18)
    - Miscellaneous Photos including Alfred House, (Maine), Willcox home, (Ithaca), and Mary (?); Negatives (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Items
    - Passport, Aug. 31, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Passport, Apr. 26, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Scrapbook: Congratulations to Walter F. Willcox from the descendants of his brother William G. Willcox," 1961 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Printed materials
    - "Sprouts from a Winter Garden," 1947-1954 by Walter F. Willcox (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - "Methods of Appointing Seats in the House of Representatives" by Walter F. Willcox. Reprint, Journal of the American Statistical Association, Dec. 1954, Vol. 49, pp. 685-695 and other related material ( 1940, 1941 ) (Box 6, Folder 24)